<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>outreach on Gabriel Nakamura</title>
    <link>/categories/outreach/</link>
    <description>Recent content in outreach on Gabriel Nakamura</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 14:15:59 -0600</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/outreach/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Invited Lecture for inaugural class to graduate program in Animal Biodiversity at UFSM (Portuguese)</title>
      <link>/talk/talk_ufsm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2023 14:15:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/talk_ufsm/</guid>
      <description>Contando Histórias em ecologia: um olhar para o passado para compreender a biodiversidade     Resumo     Uma das magias no ato de contar histórias é que elas nos transportam para lugares onde nunca pudemos estar presencialmente. Pode ser a história que a vó contava, as histórias dos filmes sobre volta para o passado, visitar outras eras como o Dr. Who. O ponto é que entender o passado e como ele afeta nossas vidas (e a vida de outros) nos fascina.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Invited Lecture to Biogeography class in Texas A&amp;M University</title>
      <link>/talk/lecture_biogeography/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 14:15:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/lecture_biogeography/</guid>
      <description>Bridging the gap among community phylogenetics, biogeography and macroevolution: moving from patterns to process     Outline     Detect patterns of biodiversity distribution essential in Community ecology and Biogeography studies, since patterns allows test hypotheses and search for the processes generating those patterns. However, this pattern-oriented approach have not shown adequate to understand the underlying processes in a given assemblage, since similar patterns can be generated by totally different evolutionary processes, and the contrary, very different patterns could be generated by the same ecological/macroevolutionary process.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My introductory presentation to Daru Lab!</title>
      <link>/talk/presentationdarulab/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Feb 2022 14:15:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/presentationdarulab/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Interview that I gave to Radio UFRGS about FishPhyloMaker package</title>
      <link>/talk/interview_ufrgs/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jan 2022 14:15:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/interview_ufrgs/</guid>
      <description>This is an interview that I conceded to Ciencia 1080, a website dedicated to promote the dissemination of scientific discoveries produced by researchers associated to the Federal University of Rio Grande do Sul (Brazil). In this interview I explained a little bit about our most recent article published in Ecological Informatics, that resulted in a software called FishPhyloMaker, as the name indicates, the main aim is to facilitate the achievement of phylogenetic hypothesis for fish species (among other functions).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quais fatores ambientais influenciam os peixes de riachos?</title>
      <link>/talk/neoticht-insta/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 May 2021 14:15:59 -0600</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/talk/neoticht-insta/</guid>
      <description>This is an outreach video that explains the main results and conclusions from a recent study that I published along with my co-authors (Yzel Súarez and Wagner Vicentin in Neotropical Ichthyology). The video is in portuguese, to read the article click here</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
