<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fish ecology on Gabriel Nakamura</title>
    <link>/categories/fish-ecology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fish ecology on Gabriel Nakamura</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/fish-ecology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>FishPhyloMaker: An R package to generate phylogenies for ray-finned fishes</title>
      <link>/publication/nakamura-etal-fishphylomaker/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/nakamura-etal-fishphylomaker/</guid>
      <description>Highlights     We provide the first automated procedure to check species names, construct phylogenetic trees and calculate Darwinian shortfalls for ray-finned fishes (Actinopterygii).
  Our R package provides functions to assemble phylogenies through a fast, reliable, and reproducible method.
  The package also provides an interactive procedure that gives more flexibility to the user when compared with other existing tools.
  The package also includes a new method to compute Darwinian shortfalls for ray-finned fishes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FishPhyloMaker: An R package to generate phylogenies for ray-finned fishes</title>
      <link>/publication/nakamura-etal-fishphylomaker_ecolinformatics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/nakamura-etal-fishphylomaker_ecolinformatics/</guid>
      <description>News   FishPhyloMaker now lives on CRAN, preprint and.. Ecological Informatics. Our article that describes the functioning of FishPhyloMaker R packages was just accepted for publication!
Abstract   Phylogenies summarize evolutionary information that is essential in the investigation of ecological and evolutionary causes of diversity patterns. They allow investigating hypotheses from trait evolution to the relationship between evolutionary diversity and ecosystem functioning. However, obtaining a comprehensive phylogenetic hypothesis can be difficult for some groups, especially those with a high number of species, that is the case for fishes, particularly tropical ones.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Taxonomic and phylogenetic beta diversity in headwater stream fish communities of the Paraná and Paraguai River basins</title>
      <link>/publication/nakamura-etal-neotropichthyol-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/nakamura-etal-neotropichthyol-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract   Patterns of species replacement and richness differences along environmental gradients or ecoregions shed light on different ecological and evolutionary mechanisms acting on community structure. Communities of aquatic ecosystems of different watersheds are supposed to host distinct species and lineages. Quantifying and understanding the degree to which these differences are affected by environmental and biogeographical factors remains an open question for these environments, particularly in the Neotropical region.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional and phylogenetic dimensions are more important than the taxonomic dimension for capturing variation in stream fish communities</title>
      <link>/publication/nakamura-etal-australecol-2018/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/nakamura-etal-australecol-2018/</guid>
      <description>Abstract   Biodiversity is inherently multidimensional in nature, differences in evolutionary history, attributes of species, taxonomic composition constitutes a small fraction of whole variation present in this multidimensional space. Despite its multidimensional characteristic, biodiversity has been traditionally measured by assessing its dimensions separately through metrics of diversity. However, assessing multiple dimensions in a common framework opens the possibility of answering interesting questions that, until now, are poorly understood, such as: What dimensions capture most of the variation present in biodiversity among communities?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
