<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Community ecology on Gabriel Nakamura</title>
    <link>/categories/community-ecology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Community ecology on Gabriel Nakamura</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/categories/community-ecology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Changes of Phylogenetic and Taxonomic Diversity of Odonata (Insecta) in Response to Land Use in Amazonia</title>
      <link>/publication/carvalho-etal-forests-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/carvalho-etal-forests-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract   Changes in natural habitats for human use can alter the distribution of biodiversity, favoring species that are more tolerant to environmental disturbance. Usually, these species comprise clades of habitat generalists, which have biological mechanisms to colonize environments with different environmental conditions. However, such effects are still poorly understood for most biological groups, such as the Amazon odonates. Therefore, this study aims to evaluate the effects of land use along an environmental gradient on the phylogenetic and taxonomic diversity of Odonata in the Amazon.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There and Back to The Present: An Evolutionary Tale on Biological Diversity</title>
      <link>/publication/duarte-etal-mcfly-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/duarte-etal-mcfly-2021/</guid>
      <description>Abstract   Ecologists often agree on the importance of macroevolution for niche-mediated distribution of biological diversity along environmental gradients. Yet, macroevolutionary diversification and dispersal in time and space generate uneven geographic distribution of phylogenetic pools, which affects the imprint let by macroevolution on local species pools. In this article we introduce an individual-based simulation approach coupled to Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) that allows to parameterize the adaptation rate of species’ niche positions along the evolution of a monophyletic lineage, and the intensity of dispersal limitation, associated with the distribution of biological diversity between assemblages potentially connected by dispersal (metacommunity).</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
